A TOHO PRODUCTION
I LIVE IN FEAR
Produced by
SOJIRO MOTOKI
Screenplay by SHINOBU HASHIMOTO,
HIDEO OGUNI, and AKIRA KUROSAWA
Director of Photography
ASAKAZU NAKAl
Production Design by
YOSHIRO MURAKI
Music by
FUMIO HAYASAKA
Edited by
CHOZO OBATA
Starring
TOSHIRO MIFUNE
TAKASHI SHIMURA
MINORU CHIAKI
MASAO SHIMIZU
EIKO MIYOSHI
KYOKO AO YAMA
HARUKO TOGO
NORIKO SENGOKU
AKEMI NEGISHI
YOICHI TACHIKAWA
KICHIJIRO UEDA, EIJIRO TONO
YUTAKA SADA
KAMATARI FUJIWARA
KEN MITSUDA
ATSUSHI WATANABE
KIYOMI MIZUNO YA, GEN SHIMIZU
TORANOSUKE OGAWA
Directed by
AKIRA KUROSAWA
HARADA DENTAL CLINIC
Father, telephone.
Just a minute.
Who is it?
- The court.
- Oh, I forgot!
The court? Why?
The dental association nominated him
to be a family court arbitrator.
Divorce suits, estate battles -
things like that.
That's tough work.
Actually, he really likes it,
though he grumbles a lot.
I have to be in court at 1:00.
Another afternoon lost.
What have I
gotten myself into?
TOKYO FAMILY COURT
DOMESTIC ADJUDICATION
JUDGE ARAKI
Please stay out here.
He's provided
for my daughter a long time -
Yes, but in this case -
We're not asking for ourselves,
but there's the baby to consider.
Please just wait here.
Why can't I go in?
I'm just as much his son as you.
Enough out of you!
How dare you talk
to us like that!
You're just his son-in-law.
She may be illegitimate,
but she's his flesh and blood.
Listen,
I don't see how this case
concerns any of you.
- Hold on!
- We have a lot at stake!
Listen, I think we all need
to discuss it,
but Father's very upset.
We need to calm him down first.
Once that's done,
everyone can have their say.
Please just wait here.
- You heard me!
- But I -
I don't know how you know Father,
but you'll have your say as well.
He's in quite a state!
Listen to me:
I'm a court mediator.
I'm terribly sorry.
Please, after you.
- Damn fools!
- Father!
I just don't -
Welcome.
I just don't get it.
This is a family matter!
Just butt out!
I'm so sorry.
Father's always like this.
Ichiro, say something.
This is too much.
Father, you see -
Fool!
We discussed it,
and we asked them to -
That's right.
We received a formal petition.
Whatever it says,
I won't recognize it!
Legally, the petition -
Father, not recognizing it
is like not recognizing us as adults.
Tell me,
does this bunch
look like adults to you?
These loafers think
about nothing but my estate!
Jackasses!
- Father!
We understand your feelings, Father.
Don't we, dear?
That's right. All Japanese
people share your anxiety.
It's just that you're a bit -
Right, Ichiro?
Just say it! I'm insane!
Why don't you listen?
Father!
Mother, please!
Don't make a scene.
Let's all just go home and -
We're here because
we can't resolve this ourselves.
We're just making
a spectacle of ourselves.
Ichiro...
do something!
This is terrible!
You're the eldest!
That's right.
You're embarrassing us all.
I'm sorry for the trouble
we've caused.
It's all right.
This is our job.
Family court exists
precisely so you have a place
to bring your troubles.
We're happy to mediate
in even the ugliest spousal disputes.
And other disputes too:
Between parents,
children, and siblings.
Life's full of disputes, and bashing
each other's heads solves nothing.
So there's no choice
but to enlist the aid of a third party.
People need to speak openly
so that resentment doesn't build.
Our job is to listen
to those pent-up frustrations.
We listen to both sides
and help you think through a solution.
So what do you say?
Why not let everyone
have their say and let us help?
Miss Tamiya,
let's get started.
Everyone please wait
in the hallway.
Father.
Not consulting with me first!
Fools!
We've got our work
cut out for us this time.
Thank you for coming.
Allow me to introduce
Mr. Hori of the bar association.
This is Dr. Harada.
- Pleased to meet you.
- Likewise.
We should examine the petition.
There's not much time,
so I'll read it aloud.
I'll skip the names
and addresses of the parties.
The aim of the petition
is as follows:
"I hereby request
that Kiichi Nakajima -"
The older gentleman.
"Be pronounced
mentally incompetent
on the grounds
that the petitioner,
wife of aforementioned
Kiichi Nakajima,
in June of last year
discovered that her husband
harbored delusional fears
about atomic and hydrogen bombs
and subsequent radioactivity...
...atomic and hydrogen bombs
and subsequent radioactivity.
In September, seeking to avoid
fallout from the south,
and despite
his entire family's opposition,
he purchased 1.6 square kilometers
of property in Akita Prefecture
and began to construct thereupon
an unusual underground dwelling.
In November,
after reading in a newspaper
that fallout
would come from the north,
he halted construction.
As a result,
the family suffered
the senseless loss
of 7.4 million yen.
Mr. Nakajima's erratic behavior
did not end there.
He now claims
that the only safe place on earth
is South America.
He has unilaterally set in motion a plan
to move all his dependents to Brazil
and has announced that
he will invest all his resources
to this end.
Unless he is declared
mentally incompetent
and subject to conservatorship,
his life and that
of all members of his family
will in all likelihood
be brought to ruin.
I therefore submit this petition
in request of said intervention. "
Listen, what will we do
if he's declared incompetent?
It could be real trouble.
He won't be able
to use his money as he wishes.
His wife will be appointed
legal conservator.
If that happens,
my daughter -
Don't worry about Asako.
Young people today are very resourceful.
Will the applicant
please step inside?
Mother.
Mother, come on.
Please spare me this.
You all go in.
Not this again!
You're the petitioner!
You have to go!
I just want -
Hurry up
and stop wasting time!
Mrs. Toyo Nakajima?
Please come in.
I'm Ichiro, the eldest son.
Jiro, second son.
I'm Yoshi, eldest daughter.
I'm Yoshi's husband.
I'm sorry, but only
those listed on the petition -
Well, I guess
I don't need to be there.
Hey, Susumu.
What do you think
about the A-bomb and the H-bomb?
What's this about?
Never mind that.
What do you think?
Are you afraid?
Of course I am.
You're really afraid?
Yes, really.
Everyone's afraid of them.
Then how can you be so calm?
Well, because...
there's nothing we can do,
is there?
Sumiko, let's eat.
- Right away.
Sorry to keep you waiting.
But what if someone
was consumed with worry?
He'd have a nervous breakdown.
No doubt about it.
You're wrong.
This wasn't a nervous breakdown
by any means.
What is this all about?
Today's case?
What happened?
I just can't figure him out.
NAKAJIMA FOUNDRY
Stop!
Okay!
Here you are.
Seven tons, 320 kilograms.
That's okay, ma'am.
Koto Gas No. 2?
It's not as good as our A1.
I'd say it's 10% -
no, 12% ash.
Mr. Ishida would like immediate
payment, even if in promissory notes.
- Price?
- 17,500 a ton.
Freight costs went up recently.
- Ash content is 9%?
- Per Tokyo Gas.
- I say it's 13%.
- Impossible!
Take off 1,500 yen per ton
and we'll pay tomorrow in cash.
You drive a hard bargain.
Ichiro, watch that furnace!
I've told you a million times!
1,500 less per ton will kill me.
Don't let him
smooth-talk you, Ichiro!
Sue, what are you saying?
Ichiro's such a pushover.
He's the one who needs
a conservator, not Father.
Watch your mouth,
little girl.
And you're the grown-up,
I suppose?
Four grown-ups spent
an entire day in court, and for what?
What?
"Calm down and come back later. "
Right?
- Watch your mouth!
- No, don't!
You still feel like quarrelling
after all that's happened?
Who's that man?
- Mr. Okamoto.
- No, the other man.
Ichiro, you know that other man?
Mrs. Nakajima...
I'm impressed!
Few people your age
have that kind of resolve.
Frankly, I was shocked
to hear of your husband's plan.
I tried to stop him,
but he's not easily dissuaded.
But the more I thought,
the more I admired his decision.
Everyone has their own
feelings on the matter:
Some want to flee Japan,
others want to come back.
I brought an old friend.
He has a big farm overseas.
This way, please.
Out of the way!
What a great idea, huh?
Almost as good as being there.
I've seen the movie.
Looks like a really nice place to live.
Look closely.
That will be your house.
I see.
What a nice house!
Who's there?
Come in.
Father!
What is it this early?
What is it, Father?
Did you lose your case?
Fool.
Don't worry about trifles.
There's this month's allowance.
If they declare you incompetent,
I'll be cut out.
Their petition be damned!
Listen, I wish
you could have seen it.
I mean,
last night we watched movies
of the farm I plan to buy.
What a wonderful place!
To be honest,
I was relieved.
Anybody who saw it
would be reassured.
Since then,
they haven't said a word.
It's all settled.
So don't fret.
Bring your mother's ashes
and come with us to Brazil.
Father...
don't worry about me.
I'm not part of your family.
I don't want to go all that way
just to be a burden.
If you could just give me
enough to get by on...
I don't mind staying behind.
I'll be fine.
What are you blabbering about?
First of all -
But -
Forget it.
Leave it all to me.
Father!
São Paulo?
Taeko, you studied it
in geography class, right?
It's not far from a town
called São Paolo.
It was a real relief
seeing that moving picture.
As far as the eye can see -
We appreciate your kind offer
to take us along, but -
Right?
Right. We couldn't
dare ask that of you.
Fools!
Why are you all so -
Never mind.
Just leave things to me.
We need to increase our stock this month.
We'll need a little extra.
Nonsense! Why stock up
when we're moving to Brazil? Fool!
- Please -
- All right, all right!
There's no way I'm going.
Who wants to move to Brazil?
São Paolo!
He's gotta be crazy!
I just don't understand.
Why are you all so concerned
about being a burden?
Your father says
it would be selfish of him
and put him more in my debt.
You should both
just come along.
Don't worry about a thing.
I'll take care of it.
What's so funny?
You think he's worried
about being selfish?
He just doesn't want to go.
Don't you want to go?
Well, I -
You don't want to go?
Hello?
Didn't you say
we meet next on the 23rd?
It's been moved up?
You see,
the gentleman in the case
has ignored our advice.
He's moving ahead
with his plan.
They say they can't
let him go on like this.
Yes, that's right.
Yes, Mr. Hori has agreed
to the new date, so -
Thank you so much.
Mr. Nakajima, express mail.
MRS. TO YO NAKAJIMA
MR. KIICHI NAKAJIMA
TOKYO FAMILY COURT
Special bulletin:
Thunderstorm moving this way.
Welcome home.
My father's plans are neither
concrete nor well thought out.
He intends to buy land
and a house in Brazil,
but where he'll find US dollars
I don't know.
Emigration is allowed if there's
a clear and constructive reason,
but he's running away
out of fear.
He can't buy more dollars
than allowed by law.
I verified that
with the Ministry of Finance.
This plan to go to Brazil
will be a waste of money,
just like his underground bunker.
Fool!
I don't need dollars
to buy that farm.
How so?
It's easy if the owner
wants to return to Japan.
I could barter
my property for his.
But that would be
circumventing the law -
No.
I see nothing illegal about it.
Actually, I'd say
it's a very clever approach.
- And you've found this farm owner?
- I have.
After you.
What about this?
Your father is
very concerned about you.
Couldn't you go along
with him on this?
As I've listened
to the various points,
I've begun to feel
that it isn't such a bad idea.
A lot of people
want to go to Brazil now,
more than the ships can carry.
I beg to disagree.
You fail to take into account
the circumstances of our lives.
Put yourself in our shoes.
We're doing fine as it is.
Why should we have to -
Right, Ichiro?
We were all born
and raised in that foundry.
Exactly. We can't imagine
living outside of it.
How dare you!
I'm the one who poured
his entire life into that foundry!
I'll miss it more than anybody!
I understand.
I realize what you're willing to endure
moving to Brazil for our sake,
and I'm grateful.
But it's an unwelcome kindness
all the same.
My husband teaches French.
What would he do in Brazil?
And how do I
become a farmer?
Fool!
Don't you realize that life
is the most precious thing?
Of course life is precious,
but everybody has to die
sooner or later.
What difference
does it make how?
Yes, try to see it that way.
Everybody has to die,
but I won't be murdered!
Let me ask you, Father:
Are we the only ones going to Brazil?
Jiro!
We can't have secrets
at a time like this!
Doctor...
you remember the people
I was arguing with last time?
They're -
I don't want to disgrace the family,
but they're my father's -
You see, I have five others
besides these here to support:
Two mistresses,
their two children,
and a son
by a mistress now dead.
And I intend
to take them all with me!
You see?
It's utter insanity!
Maybe we could bear it,
but my mother -
Jiro, I'll be -
Mother, speak up!
You can't go on suffering in silence!
Now you see
how absurdly selfish he is.
Self-centered and selfish!
We've been victims
of his selfishness for too long.
Father, if you must go to Brazil,
go by yourself.
Hell, take your mistresses
and bastard kids too.
Just count us out.
You ungrateful bastard!
Miss Sué, over here!
Is the owner in?
Father? He's in court.
I thought
the case was dropped.
They're deciding today.
Where did Father go?
He didn't go home, did he?
Don't be silly.
Let him go home
if he wants.
If he does, we win.
First of all -
It seems to me
we have no choice
but to grant their petition.
Dr. Harada?
That's it then.
Just a moment, please.
When we declare people
incompetent
due to fiscal irresponsibility,
it's usually for wasting money
on women, alcohol, and gambling.
But taking precautions
against A-bombs -
In general, that's true.
But his behavior goes
far beyond common sense.
That's right. His psychiatric tests
showed no abnormalities,
but he's gone too far.
That's my point:
His only fault is going too far.
But his anxiety about the bomb
is something we all share.
Mr. Araki, Mr. Hori, Miss Tamiya -
you all know that feeling.
Isn't that true?
We just don't feel it
quite as strongly.
We don't build underground shelters
or plan to move to Brazil.
But can we claim that the feeling
is beyond comprehension?
The Japanese all share it,
to greater or lesser degrees.
We can't dispense with it so easily
by just saying he went too far -
I'm approaching this
as a practical problem.
The old man feels as he does,
but his family doesn't feel
like going to Brazil with him.
Forcing them to go
would violate their rights.
Suppose we leave
the situation as it is.
He's sure to sell
his house and foundry.
His family will lose its livelihood
and be left on the street.
Yes, that's what the investigator's
report concluded.
That's right.
To prevent that, we have
to declare him incompetent.
I understand that.
Nonetheless...
why have we deliberated
at such length
if it's that simple?
In any event, we can't
look at him and remain unmoved.
That's because
his fear of the bomb
is palpable and real
in a way that neither we
nor his family can grasp.
But why does he feel it so strongly?
What triggered it?
We should try hard
to figure that out.
Anxiety?
No, I feel nothing of the sort.
Then why the hurry
to go to Brazil?
I believe the bomb
can be avoided.
Why let them kill you
if you have a choice?
That's why I'm in a hurry.
It's the cowards who tremble
and close their eyes to reality.
My children
are a good example.
Cowards, eh?
Alas, I'm afraid
that includes us.
So what do we do now?
What choice do we have?
Dr. Harada,
look at it from this angle:
It's obvious
the man's being rash.
He's grappling with a problem
too big for any one individual.
If he keeps on like this,
he'll get himself into real trouble.
Isn't restraining him
before it's too late
really the kindest thing
we can do?
Miss Tamiya.
Will you all come in, please?
Father, it's 11:00.
What are you reading?
THE ASHES OF DEATH
Are you all right? Don't tell me
you want to go to Brazil too.
Read it yourself.
If the birds and beasts could read it,
they'd all flee Japan.
Susumu.
This whole thing leaves
a bad taste in my mouth.
You mean the case?
Don't let it get to you.
The old man won't give up that easily.
He appealed right away, of course.
Now it goes to a higher court.
Good.
It's no longer
your responsibility.
This is wonderful!
For 30 years
I've seen this view in my dreams.
It looks closer in winter.
I'd like to breed cattle here.
I'm a farmer. I wouldn't know
what to do with your foundry.
Would you buy this land
for me instead?
How big is it?
I'd guess about 60 acres.
The area is about 20 chobu.
What's the price?
8.2 million yen.
Isn't that kind of expensive?
In Brazil we could buy
24,000 acres for that amount.
What about a deposit?
I'd need one soon.
I've got
another interested buyer.
I'm asking how much!
1.5 million.
Jiro, are you sure
this is proper?
We have no choice.
We don't know what Father's up to.
Or what you'll be up to either,
once you get that combination.
Ichiro, any news?
- Well?
- It's serious!
Water!
Well?
Our vendors didn't know that
Father was declared incompetent.
They paid company bills
directly to him!
How much altogether?
I wonder what he's planning.
How much?
Kitakawa, 280,000.
Nakatsuka, 430,000.
Takano, 160,000. Omori, 150,000.
Hamaguchi, 200,000.
Is that it?
1,220,000 yen.
That much?
That's Dad for you.
Only took him two days.
Stop it, you stupid jerk!
Let me have that term deposit
certificate I gave your mother.
What for?
I need money in a hurry.
Lend it to me.
Don't worry.
I'm about to -
I know.
But no matter
how many times you appeal,
I don't think you'll win.
Fool! I'll win!
I wonder.
You little bastard!
After everything I've done!
That money's
the only thing I can count on.
The deed to the shop?
I need it as collateral
for a loan.
I'll give it back in no time.
No, I won't do it!
Besides, when are you going
to put Taeko in your family register?
First you leave her out,
and now you take the shop!
Of course
I'll acknowledge her.
Well...
we'll talk about the deed
after you do that.
What? You spent it?
I'm sorry.
What were you thinking?
Fool!
What's wrong?
I sent him to cash
a promissory note for 200,000 yen.
That's like trusting
a cat with milk.
I was in a hurry.
Cough it up.
What?
Don't act dumb!
The money!
- I spent it.
- You couldn't have spent it all.
In half a day?
You wouldn't dare.
- There's nothing left!
- Liar!
Is this really all?
You gave some to that woman!
What are you talking about?
I'll find out soon enough.
It was hard keeping this
hidden from you, Father.
I saved it from my allowance.
It's not enough
to cover the loss, but -
Even the 200,000
wasn't enough. Forget it.
What's the matter?
This isn't like you.
There's no point in going in
without enough!
Why don't you explain what happened
and just apologize like a man?
That's what I'd do.
You really are
a good and honest man.
I admire you very much.
Very well. I'll wait.
But...
I can't stay in Tokyo forever.
I'd planned to leave
in a few days.
Don't worry.
This is a gentlemen's agreement.
When your affairs are settled,
come visit the farm.
Meanwhile,
take your money back.
You know, when my father
wanted to emigrate to Brazil,
I fought him tooth and nail.
Then our house
burned down in a fire.
That forced me
to change my mind.
That's how people are.
I understand
your sons' concern.
Return this money
to them for now.
Discuss it with them amicably.
They're your children,
after all.
It's all there.
Wait a minute, Ichiro.
Let's let Father
spend it as he likes.
That will settle
the case once and for all.
Don't you see?
He'll prove that he's incompetent.
What the -
Fool!
What's the point
of getting angry?
It's not our fault.
You created this situation.
I obtained a court injunction
against disposal of our assets
while we await your appeal.
Nobody can spend a yen
without the court's permission.
What you've been doing
is clearly illegal.
You've already ensured
that your appeal will be rejected.
But Father brought back
the money.
We won't accept it.
Jiro, apologize!
Those things
sure make travel easier!
In four days
he'll be back in Brazil.
Quite a man, isn't he?
You can rest easy too.
Excuse me.
Aren't you Mr. Nakajima?
Remember me?
I'm Dr. Harada.
Harada, from family court.
Mr. Nakajima!
What do you want?
Well, nothing
in particular, but -
Then you'll excuse me.
I must tell you one thing,
you and the others
who ruled against me.
I told you then
I wasn't afraid of the bomb.
But just look at me now!
Can't you see?
I'm out of my mind with fear!
And it's you
who made me like this!
Thanks to you,
there's nothing I can do.
Nothing!
I keep thinking
about the H-bomb,
but all I can do is think!
And the more I think,
the more restless I become.
But there's nothing I can do!
It's a living hell!
But really...
is there anything else
we could have done?
That case has been
very much on my mind too.
But no matter how you look at it,
there was no other possible solution.
Even forgetting
my role as judge
and approaching
the problem as his ally,
there'd be no way
to save him from his misery.
That misery
is nobody's fault, really.
It simply stems from the fact
that the H-bomb exists,
and from his rather
unusual disposition.
His mind has no sense
of proper limits.
He thinks far too much -
about everything.
Sir...
this spooky weather
doesn't let up, does it?
The newspapers say
it's from an H-bomb test.
You probably know
better than anyone,
but they say that
even if a bomb is dropped
on China, or America,
or Russia,
the fallout will eventually
drift over Japan.
I don't really understand it.
Something to do
with atmospheric currents.
Japan's a sort of valley
that all radioactivity flows into.
But what about those of us
living in that valley?
What will happen to us?
First our hair will fall out.
In the end our bones
will crumble and rot.
Not something
to look forward to, eh?
The other day I saw a report
on the bomb damage in Hiroshima.
It was really gruesome.
I'll bet you saw it too.
- A baby his age -
- Stop it!
Terribly sorry, sir.
I should've realized
it's already weighing on your mind.
But even worry
has to be done in moderation.
You know, you can't
do anything without money.
Please don't be too stubborn.
Make peace with your sons
and get as much as you can.
You're in a good position.
Even if you've been
declared incompetent,
you could still
retire comfortably.
Whereas we can't afford
to support you here -
Is he asleep?
Thanks.
What's wrong?
This just won't do.
You haven't slept for days.
THE TRUTH ABOUT THE H-BOMB -
A WEAPON TO DESTRO Y HUMANITY
Madness,
inventing such a thing!
Where are you going?
Home.
All of you come with me!
What?
How could I face them?
Never mind that!
Just come!
Thank you.
Sorry for the bother.
Father, why have you
gathered us all here?
I'm begging you,
on my life.
Come to Brazil with me.
I beg of you.
All of you, as one family.
You say I'm paranoid,
and maybe I am.
But H-bombs really exist.
War could break out
at any time.
If it does,
it'll be too late to get away.
We can still make it.
Let's flee while we can.
I can't let him die.
I can't let an H-bomb kill him
before he's even had a chance to live!
I don't care about myself,
and I thought
I'd have to give up on you.
I thought at one point
if I could at least save this baby -
But you're all
my flesh and blood!
I can't leave you here!
Please come with me,
I'm begging you.
Look, he wrote
to me from Brazil.
Listen to how kind he is:
"Come at once.
I'll get you permanent residence. "
He's like a Buddha
come to save us from hell.
We can build
a good life there.
Even a stranger
is this kind to us.
I beg you:
Come with me to Brazil.
I'm begging you.
Everybody, please,
let's go with him.
Look how he's begging you.
I'm begging you too.
Please go with him.
Has Father ever
been wrong about anything?
He's always tried
to plan ahead,
not for himself,
but for all of us.
Let's go, Ichiro.
Jiro, let's go.
Let's go, Yoshiko.
Why don't you say anything?
Why are you all so quiet?
Father, I'll go with you!
Father!
He's exhausted.
He needs rest.
The injection
will help him fall asleep.
I don't want
to stay here any longer.
Well?
There are more pressing matters
than getting in the family register.
What if he passes away?
We need to be put in his will.
His will?
Didn't you get a dowry
when you married?
Almost nothing. He needed
capital then for the foundry.
Anyway, property can't be transferred
unless stated in his will.
You talk
like a lawyer nowadays.
His will?
What's that? His will?
They want to be included in it.
That's horrible!
It's like they want him to die.
Just a minute.
Maybe that's best.
It would make things clear.
Then Jiro couldn't talk to you
like he just did.
He's sleepy, right?
He can sleep in my room.
This way.
Come on, it's okay.
- Father's asleep, so you can go home.
- Yes, but -
In court you said we'd have
a chance to discuss these things.
Perhaps I did,
but now's not the time.
We hate to ask
at a time like this,
but now's precisely
when we need to discuss it.
He's right.
I could talk to Father
about it for you.
Father's fast asleep.
The doctor said
it's the best thing for him.
Pestering a sick man
about his will is going too far.
Please forgive me.
It's really
not my place to be here.
Mother, look at the baby.
He looks just like Father!
It's no big deal.
Right, Mother?
What are you saying?
She doesn't hold it
against you.
She just doesn't want to set
a bad example for her children.
You silly girl!
Care to take a look?
Are these all your relatives?
Even Father
doesn't get around that much!
That's last year's
factory outing at the beach.
We had such
a lovely time that day.
It was really wonderful.
But you know...
it was so much fun
that I knew some misfortune
would come along.
I was so afraid,
and I was right.
- I guess we're going to Brazil!
- Well, I'm not!
It seems
Mother and Sue are going.
- With what money?
- What money?
If Mother withdraws her petition,
the court will release the money.
Then what will happen to us?
We'll probably get some too.
But not much,
staying against Father's wishes.
What about the foundry?
That's why we have
to fight selling it.
We have to hold on to that
if nothing else.
The foundry's the important thing.
As long as we have that...
- Where's the Nakajima foundry?
- Around that corner.
- There was a terrible accident.
- A real tragedy.
I demand an explanation!
Explain yourself,
you son of a bitch!
Can you think
of any other cause?
You said you forgot
to quench the coals!
Foreman, don't you remember
how strict Father was about that?
"Always check the work area. "
Look at Father!
Boss, please forgive me!
No, it was me.
I set this fire.
Don't try to protect them.
The police will be here to investigate.
I tell you,
I started the fire!
You're talking nonsense
from the shock.
Mother!
Take Father inside!
Jiro, because of this foundry,
you all refused to leave Japan
and go to Brazil with me.
I thought with the foundry
out of the way -
Sue.
Sue, did you see
what happened?
Sue, answer me!
Why don't you say anything?
Sue, tell me what happened!
Sue, what happened?
You were the first
to discover the fire.
What did you see
from this window?
Tell them who came
out of the foundry as the fire started!
Don't cry.
We'll be all right.
We may have lost the foundry,
but we have enough
to live on in Brazil.
Boss, you mean...
you don't care what happens
to the rest of us?
Is that it, boss?
You don't care
if the rest of us starve?
You've completely
lost your senses!
You don't care
what happens to us?
I was wrong. Forgive me.
I'll find a way to take you all.
I was wrong to think
only of my family.
You're right.
We all have to survive.
Every one of us.
I beg you,
come with me to Brazil.
With what money?
I seriously doubt
these workers want to go to Brazil.
You can be so selfish.
And what about
that old man from Brazil?
You call him a Buddha, then ask him
to die in your place! We're not going!
I understand.
I'll talk to him.
I'll find a different farm.
We can survive if we work hard.
We can even go to the Amazon.
It doesn't matter
where you go.
No place on earth
is safe from the H-bomb.
Just 400 tons can kill all life!
There's more than that now!
Shut up, you pompous ass!
Have you given it
even a moment's thought?
Father's been racked with worry
for all of our sakes,
while you think
of nothing but yourselves!
This guy set fire
to his own house.
For the insurance?
Same old story.
But this one's a real oddball.
Quiet down!
H- bombs?
You're a fool
to worry about that stuff.
Leave that
to the prime minister.
Pops, if you're so afraid,
why not move to another planet?
PSYCHIATRIC WARD NO. 3
You know,
maybe he'll be happier this way.
Dr. Harada, isn't it?
Thank you for everything.
Don't mention it.
Please accept my sympathies.
Have you come to see him?
I feel...
guilty about what's happened.
I wonder if the court
perhaps made the wrong decision.
Come now.
If anyone's to blame, it's us.
We shouldn't have
taken him to court.
We should have
brought him here.
That would have been better
for all concerned, including Father.
Anyway,
I'll let you go see him.
Good-bye now.
Whenever I see this patient,
I become terribly depressed.
This is the first time
that's happened to me.
Of course the insane
are depressing to be around.
That said...
whenever I see him...
I somehow feel...
oddly anxious...
even though I'm the one
who's supposed to be sane.
Is he crazy?
Or are we, who can remain
unperturbed in an insane world,
the crazy ones?
This way, please.
It's Dr. Harada.
I'm glad you came.
Yes, I'm very glad you came.
You're safe here.
Have no fear.
By the way...
what happened to the Earth?
Are many people
still left behind there?
Are there still
many people there?
That's not good.
Not good at all.
They'd better escape soon
or they'll be sorry!
Why don't they understand?
They better hurry
and come to this planet!
They better hurry -
Is it burning?
The Earth is burning!
It's burning!
The Earth has finally
gone up in flames!
THE END